Guide to the Teachers Action Caucus (United Federation of Teachers) Records TAM.141
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Teachers Action Caucus (United Federation of Teachers) Records
1968-1994
TAM.141
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
The Teachers Action Caucus, founded in 1968 as Teachers for Community Control, was a rank and file opposition group within the United Federation of Teachers (New York City) that was founded by former members of the radical Teachers' Union of the City of New York (1916-1964), many of whose leading activists were Communists, and by younger teachers representing the New Left of the 1960s. The records contain agendas, circulars, clippings, correspondence, fliers, minutes, newsletters, and petitions documenting the Caucus' campaigns for union offices, for union democracy and improved working conditions, for community participation in the administration of the school system, and in opposition to the domestic and foreign policy positions taken by the leadership of the United Federation of Teachers and its president, Albert Shanker.
Teachers Action Caucus.
Provenance
Gift of Anne L. Filardo, 2000.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Teachers Action Caucus, as Teachers for Community Control, was a rank and file opposition group within the United Federation of Teachers (New York City) that was founded by former members of the radical Teachers' Union of the City of New York (1916-1964), many of whose leading activists were Communists, and by younger teachers representing the New Left of the 1960s. While the impetus for the Caucus' founding in 1968 was its objection to the UFT's position relating to the impending crisis in relations between the UFT and the African American community that erupted in the teachers' strike later that year, TAC went on to oppose the leadership of the UFT on a broad range of issues relating to its education, labor, and domestic and foreign policy positions. With the rise of the New Action Coalition, a coalition of progressive teachers, in the late 1980s-early 1990s, in which TAC members participated, TAC became less active and eventually ceased to exist.
Sources:
The 1968 New York City school crisis: Teacher politics, racial politics and the decline of liberalism/ by Daniel Hiram Perlstein. PhD dissertation, Stanford University, 1994.
Justice, justice: school politics and the eclipse of liberalism/ by Daniel H. Perlstein. New York: Peter Lang, 2004.
Scope and Content Note
The records contain agendas, circulars, clippings, correspondence, fliers, minutes (including some UFT executive board minutes), newsletters, and petitions documenting the Caucus' campaigns for union offices, for union democracy and contract enforcement, improved working conditions, for community participation in the administration of the school system, for an alliance with African American and other community interests on behalf of greater funding for the New York City school system, and in opposition to the domestic and foreign policy positions taken by the leadership of the United Federation of Teachers and its president, Albert Shanker, in particular those involving education reform, the Vietnam War, and international labor activities. Notable files include those dealing with the 1968 teachers' strike and its aftermath, and those from 1984-1987 pertaining to the campaigns of TAC member Michael Shulman for the position of Vice-President for academic high schools (he was elected in 1985).
Arrangement
The folders are arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into one series:
I, Records
Filardo, Anne Levine, 1922-; New Action Coalition (United Federation of Teachers).; Ocean Hill-Brownsville Demonstration School District (New York, N.Y.).; Shanker, Albert.; Shulman, Michael.; Teachers Action Caucus.; United Federation of Teachers.; African Americans |x Education |x Social aspects.; African Americans |x Relations with Jews.; Agendas (administrative records); Circulars (fliers); Civil rights |z New York (State) |z New York.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Community and school |z New York (State) |z New York.; Correspondence.; Discrimination in education |z New York (State) |z New York.; Educational equalization |z New York (State) |z New York.; Fliers (printed matter); Labor union democracy |z New York (State) |z New York.; Minorities |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York.; Minutes.; Newsletters.; Petitions.; Schools |x Decentralization |z New York (State) |z New York.; Strikes and lockouts |x Teachers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Teachers |x Workload |z New York (State) |z New York.; Teachers' unions |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Series I: Records
  - Perlstein, Dan. The 1968 New York City school crisis: Teacher politics, racial politics and the decline of liberalism. PhD. Dissertation, Stanford University, 1994. Chapter 1 "Introduction;" Chapter 3 "Teachers for Community Control and the Limits of Anti-Racism." (Box 1, Folder 0.1)
  - Teachers for Community Control - part 1, Jun 1968-Jun 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Teachers for Community Control - part 2, Sep 1968-Aug 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Teachers Action Committee, Sep 1969-Aug 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Teachers Action Committee, Sep 1970-Jun 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1971-Aug 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1972-Jul 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1973-Jun 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1974-Aug 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1975-Aug 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1976-Aug 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1977-Jun 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1978-Jun 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Oct 1979-Aug 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1980-Aug 1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Oct 1981-Jul 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1982-Jun 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Oct 1983-Jul 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1984-Jun 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Jun 1985-Aug 1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1985-Dec 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Dec 1985-Jun 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1986-Mar 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Mar 1987-Jul 1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1987-Aug 1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1988-Jul 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Sep 1989-Jul 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, Aug 1990-Jan 1997 (Box 3, Folder 6)